Jan de Swart Papers
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Jan de Swart papers
1916-1994
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
de Swart, Jan
3.8 linear feet
The papers of southern California sculptor and inventor Jan de Swart measure 3.8 linear feet and are dated 1916-1994. They consist of correspondence, records concerning de Swart??s inventions, writings, printed material, miscellaneous records, and photographs.
Biographical Note
Jan de Swart (1908-1987) was a sculptor and inventor that lived and worked primarily in southern California.
Jan de Swart was born in Breda, Holland in 1908. At age 13, he began a five-year apprenticeship in the atelier of Master Yonkers in S'Hertgenbosch, run by a famous carver of ecclesiastical sculpture and furniture, and then completed compulsory military service before emigrating to the United States in 1929.
During his early years in California, de Swart worked as a furniture maker. He prospected for gold in Arizona, and lived in an artists' colony at Calabasas, California, during the 1930s, eventually settling in Eagle Rock, outside of Los Angeles, where he remained for the rest of his life. In the 1940s, he devoted himself to sculpture in wood, metal, and plastic, and participated in many exhibitions. His many commissions included murals, jewelry, furniture, and sculptured screens in a wide variety of media.
In addition, de Swart was an inventor who held over 100 scientific patents. Many of his inventions were for rivets, grommets, and other types of fasteners used for ships, aircraft, and machinery; he also developed a strong, honey-combed core material that was used for a variety of structural purposes.
He died in 1987 after suffering a heart attack.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of southern California sculptor and inventor Jan de Swart measure 3.8 linear feet and are dated 1916-1994. They consist of correspondence, records concerning de Swart's inventions, writings, printed material, miscellaneous records, and photographs.
Correspondence mostly concerns de Swart's career as an artist and, to a lesser extent, his personal life. Series 2: Invention Files documents many of de Swart's inventions through drawings, patents, contracts, licensing and royalty agreements, printed material, and related correspondence.
Writings by de Swart consist of "Notes on My Film Metamorphoses" and brief notes for remarks to students during the run of his exhibition at San Fernando Valley State University. Included among the writings by other authors is an extensive manuscript by Ursula de Swart about her life and that of her husband. Printed material includes articles about Jan de Swart, exhibition reviews, exhibition catalogs and announcements, and an article by Jan and Ursula de Swart about plastic as a sculptural medium.
Among the miscellaneous records are a few biographical notes, guest books from many of de Swart's exhibitions, and pencil drawings by Jacobs and Jock D. Peters. The 1942 calendar/diary of Ursel Peters (Ursula de Swart) records her marriage to Jan de Swart. A grant proposal for the completion of Jan ?? A Tribute to Jan de Swart, a film by Judith Bronowski and Lauren Rickey, includes biographical information and photographs.
Photographs are of artwork by Jan de Swart, exhibition installations, people (among them Jan and Ursula de Swart, and their granddaughter), places (including "Allegro," the de Swart home, and de Swart's studio), miscellaneous topics, and a photograph album of de Swart's work. Also included are a large number of negatives, slides, and transparencies.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Correspondence, 1925-1991 (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 2: Invention Files, 1930-1980 (Box 1; 0.5 linear ft.)
Series 3: Writings, 1920-1983 (Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1919-1994 (Boxes 2, 4; 0.3 linear ft.)
Series 5: Miscellaneous Records, 1916-1989 (Boxes 2, 4; 14 folders)
Series 6: Photographs, 1933-1987 (Boxes 2-4, OVs 5-14; 2.5 linear ft.)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects-Topical:
Modernism (Art); Sculptors -- California -- Los Angeles; Inventors -- California -- Los Angeles
Types of Materials:
Blueprints; Drawings; Photographs; Slides (photographs); Visitors' books; Essays; Manuscripts; Notes; Patents
Names:
De Swart, Ursula
Provenance
Gift of the artist's son, Jock de Swart, in 1996, with an addition received in 2001.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence, 1925-1991, Series 1:; (Box 1; 5 folders)
  Correspondence documents de Swart's artistic career and, to a lesser extent, his personal life. Additional correspondence is found in Series 2: Invention Files.
  Correspondence is arranged in chronological order.
  - Correspondence, 1925-1991, undated, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence regarding Miscellaneous Commissions, 1947-1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Inventions, 1930-1980, Series 2:; (Box 1; 0.5 linear ft.)
  This series consists of drawings, patents, contracts, licensing and royalty agreements, printed material, and correspondence relating to de Swart's inventions.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Agreements, Royalty Statements, Related Correspondence, 1942-1965, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Applicator Tool for Electrical Pass-Throughs, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bolts, 1945-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bottle Cap, 1954-1957, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bottle Carrier, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Container Closure, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Core Material, 1949-1973, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Core Material (American Thermoform Corp. v. Jess R. Hale), 1977-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence with Charles A. Breskin (agent) and Lawyers, 1942-1969, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with Mr. Martin, Progress Reports, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Dispensers, 1945-1950 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Door Knobs, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fastener, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Grommets and Grommet Applicator, 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lipstick Holder, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lists of Patents, 1941-1947 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous Inventions, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Paper Clip, Plastic, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Pass-Through Insulator, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Products Incorporating de Swart Patents, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Rivet, Plastic, 1952-1959 (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Rivets and Rivet Applicator, 1947-1949, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Self-Closing Top, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Shelf Supports, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Unidentified Inventions, 1930-1945, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Writings, 1920-1983, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.3 linear ft.)
  This series is arranged as 2 subseries:
  3.1: Writings By de Swart, circa 1974
  3.2: Writings By Other Authors, 1920-1983
  - Writings by de Swart, circa 1974, 3.1:
    - "Notes on My Film Metamorphoses," undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "To the Students of SFVS" (San Fernando Valley State), circa 1974 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Writings by Other Authors, 1920-1983, 3.2:
    - de Swart, Ursula (Box 1)
      - "This is about the Lives of Ursula and Jan de Swart?," undated, (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 34-37)
      - "The Fairytale Grandmother," 1954 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Travers, David. "de Swart ? de Swart," 1969 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Unknown Authors (Box 1)
      - Christmas Play, "The Street of Hearts," 1941 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      - Lists of Artwork (consignments, inventories, price lists), 1968-1983, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
      - "Report on the Jan de Swart Exhibit March 15-April 10," undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
      - Untitled Manuscripts (in German), 1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Various Authors, Inspirational Quotations, undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Printed Material, 1919-1994, Series 4:; (Boxes 2, 4; 0.3 linear ft.)
  - Articles (Box 2)
    - About or Mentioning de Swart, 1944-1993, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - About Jock D. Peters, 1920-1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - About Miscellaneous Topics, 1919-1964, undated, (see also: Box 4) (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - By Jan and Ursula de Swart, "A Medium for Sculpture" in Modern Plastics (Nov. issue), 1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements (Box 2)
    - de Swart, 1945-1994, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Other Artists, 1962-1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Exhibition Reviews (de Swart), 1945-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Items Mentioning de Swart, 1948-1989 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Poems by Ursel Peters (Ursula de Swart), in Flights, Literary Magazine of Eagle Rock High School, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Postcards and Reproductions, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Oversized Articles about Miscellaneous Topics, 1933, (see also: Box 2, F3) (Box 4 (sol))
- Miscellaneous Records, 1916-1989, Series 5:; (Boxes 2, 4; 14 folders)
  - Artwork, Pencil Drawing by Jock D. Peters and Jacobs, 1916-1928, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Biographical Data, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Business Cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Calendar/Diary of Ursel Peters/Ursula de Swart, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Grant Proposal, Judith Bronowski and Lauren Rickey, "Application for Grant Funds to Complete the Film Project Jan ?? A Tribute to Jan de Swart," undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Guest Books, 1968-1989, (6 vols. in 3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Scrapbook, 1950s, (see: Box 4) (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ticket to Olympic Games, Los Angeles (Ursel Peters/Ursula de Swart), 1932 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Oversized Scrapbook, 1950s, (loose pages; see also Box 2, F 20) (Box 4 (sol))
- Photographs, 1933-1987, Series 6:; (Boxes 2-4, OVs 5-14; 2.5 linear ft.)
  This series is arranged as 7 subseries:
  6.1: Artwork, circa 1940s-circa 1980s
  6.2: Exhibition Installations, 1984-1986
  6.3: Miscellaneous Subjects, circa 1940s-circa 1980s
  6.4: People, 1961-1987
  6.5: Places, circa 1940s-circa 1980s
  6.6: Photograph Album, circa 1940s-circa 1980s
  6.7: Negatives, Slides, Transparencies, 1933-1985
  - Artwork, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, 6.1:
    - Artwork By de Swart (Box 2)
      - Furniture, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Lucite Sculpture, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Metal Sculpture, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - "Sold (by trade) to Geo. Turner for Jock's and Ulli's estate planning," undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Wood Sculpture, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Unsorted, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (5 folders; see also: OVs 5-11) (Box 2, Folder 27-31)
    - Artwork by Other Artists, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Oversized, Unsorted Artwork by de Swart, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also Box 2, F 27-31) (Box OV 5)
    - Oversized, Unsorted Artwork by de Swart, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also Box 2, F 27-31) (Box OV 6)
    - Oversized, Unsorted Artwork by de Swart, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also Box 2, F 27-31) (Box OV 7)
    - Oversized, Unsorted Artwork by de Swart, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also Box 2, F 27-31) (Box OV 8)
    - Oversized, Unsorted Artwork by de Swart, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also Box 2, F 27-31) (Box OV 9)
    - Oversized, Unsorted Artwork by de Swart, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also Box 2, F 27-31) (Box OV 10)
    - Oversized, Unsorted Artwork by de Swart, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also Box 2, F 27-31) (Box OV 11)
  - Exhibition Installations, 1984-1986, 6.2:
    - Laguna Art Museum, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Unidentified Locations, 1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Miscellaneous Subjects, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, 6.3:
    - Chairs, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see: OV 12) (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Flowers, Wreath, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Inventions, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Ursula de Swart Projects, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see: OV 13) (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Oversized, Chairs, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also: Box 2, F 35) (Box OV 12)
    - Oversized, Ursula de Swart Projects, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also: Box 2, F 38) (Box OV 13)
  - People, 1961-1987, 6.4:
    - Jan de Swart, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Jan de Swart at Work/in Studio, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Jan de Swart with Others, 1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Jan and Ursula de Swart (wife); Jan and Lisi de Swart (granddaughter), 1979-1987, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Jock de Swart [?] (son), undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Lisi de Swart (granddaughter), undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Ursula de Swart (wife); Ursula de Swart with Others, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Unidentified Individuals, 1961, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Places, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, 6.5:
    - "Allegro" (de Swart home), circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Studio, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also: OV 14) (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Oversized, de Swart Studio, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (see also: Box 2, F 48) (Box OV 14)
  - Photograph Album, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, 6.6:
    - Photograph Album, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 4 (sol))
  - Negatives, Slides, Transparencies, 1933-1985, 6.7:
    People include Jan de Swart at work, and with his wife (Ursula de Swart) and his granddaughter (Lisi de Swart). There are also separate images of Ursula de Swart and Lisi de Swart, as well as a number of unidentified individuals.
    - Negatives (Box 3)
      - Artwork by de Swart, circa 1940s-circa 1980s, (in 4 x 6 card file) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous Subjects, People, Places, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Slides (Box 3)
      - Artwork by de Swart, 1970s-1980s, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
      - Exhibition Installations (Box 3)
        - Chicago Tower (includes opening), 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        - San Fernando Valley State College, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous Subjects, Tea Service, Welcome Banner, Wreath, 1974-1983 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - People, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Places (Box 3)
        - "Allegro" (de Swart home), 1971-1985, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
        - Tunisia, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
        - Unidentified Landscapes, 1980-1983, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Stereo Slides, Various Unidentified Subjects, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Transparencies (Box 3)
      - Artwork by de Swart (Box 3)
        - Kaiser Screen, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
        - Unsorted, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - People, Unidentified Individuals, circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Places, "Allegro" (de Swart home), circa 1940s-circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 17)